[
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 1,
        "year": 2012,
        "question": "<p> Highlight six characteristics of a democratic government.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>(a)(i) There should be majority rule.</p><p>(ii) Tolerance of opposition.</p><p>(iii) Protection of minority interests.</p><p>(iv) Provision for and guaranteeing of Fundamental Human Rights.</p><p>(v) Respect for the Rule of Law.</p><p>(vi) Independence of the Judiciary.</p><p>(vii) Periodic, free and fair elections.</p><p>(viii) Universal adult suffrage.</p><p>(ix) Existence of multi-party system</p><p>(x) Independent mass media/freedom of expression.</p><p>(xi) Existence of Public Complains Commission/Ombudsman.</p><p>(xii) Independent electoral commission.</p><p>(xiii) Fixed term/Tenure of office for political office holders.</p><p>(xiv) Existence of a constitution. </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 2,
        "year": 2012,
        "question": "<p>(a) What is independence of the judiciary?</p><p>(b) State three reasons for the independence of the judiciary </p>",
        "answer": "<p>(a) Judicial independence is the freedom of the judiciary to administer justice without any interference or influence from either the legislature or executive.</p><p>(b) (i) To enable judges to discharge their duties impartially.</p><p>(ii) To prevent the courts from being intimidated or misused.</p><p>(iii) To protect the liberty of the people.</p><p>(iv) To ensure the pub-c confidence in the judiciary.</p><p>(v) To serve as independent arbiter for the interpretation of the constitution and other laws.</p><p>(vi) To prevent abuse of power by government functionaries.</p><p>(vii) To promote strict observance of the rule of Law.</p><p>(viii) To guarantee the tenure of office of the judges. </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 3,
        "year": 2012,
        "question": "<p>Give three functions and three limitations of the legislature.</p>",
        "answer": "<p><em><strong>Functions:                                                                                                                                                                                                                          </strong></em>(i) Law making.</p><p>(ii) Approval of budget.</p><p>(iii) Approval of Presidential nominees.</p><p>(iv) Impeachment De public officers/passing a vote of no confidence.</p><p>(v) Discussion of national issues.</p><p>(vi) Ratification of treaties an: external agreements.</p><p>(vii) Investigatory/Oversight functions.</p><p>(viii) It serves as a link between the people a-c: government.</p><p>(ix) It is responsible for amending the constitution and other laws.</p><p>(x) It performs judicial functions e.g. House of Lords in Britain.</p><p>(xi) It serves as an electoral college.</p><p>(xii) It considers and deals with public petitions, complaints and grievances.</p><p>(xiii) It repeals unwanted laws.</p><p>(xiv) Approval of declaration of war, and state of emergency.</p><p>(xv) Checks and controls delegated legislation.</p><p>(xvi) It approves the creation of new states/regions/ local government areas.</p><p><strong>Limitations:                                                                                                                                                                                                                  </strong>(I)Constitutional limitation.</p><p>(ii) Judicial limitation e.g. judicial review of laws passed by the legislature.</p><p>(iii) Executive limitation e.g. dissolution of parliament in the cabinet system/veto power in the presidential system.</p><p>(iv) House rules/Standing Orders of the House.</p><p>(v) Pressure groups.</p><p>(vi) The mass media/Public opinion</p><p>(vii) International organization.</p><p>(viii) Time/Period limitation.</p><p>(ix) The Mace limits the activities of the legislature.</p><p>(x) Quorum places limitation on the legislature.</p><p>(xi) Inadequate funding.</p><p>(xii) Party discipline.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 4,
        "year": 2012,
        "question": "<p>Identify six merits of pressure groups in a democratic state</p>",
        "answer": "<p>(i) Serve as check against dictatorship.</p><p>(ii) Help to prevent bribery and corruption through their activities.</p><p>(iii) Provide useful information in the process of law making.</p><p>(iv) Assist in policy formulation and implementation.</p><p>(v) Provide educational programmes seminar, lectures, debates, etc.</p><p>(vi) Conduct research useful for the administration of the state on technical issues.</p><p>(vii) Serve as link between the people and the government.</p><p>(viii) Serve as yardstick for measuring the popularity of government policies.</p><p>(lix) Assist in championing the cause of the under privileged in the country.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 5,
        "year": 2012,
        "question": "<p>(a) What is civil service?</p><p>(b) Explain the structure of the civil service.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>(a) The Civil Service is the administrative arm of the executive organ of government responsible for formulating and executing government policies.</p><p>(b)(i)Administrative class: They advice the minister on policy matters.</p><p>(ii) Professional class: The offer professional/technical advice to the management on technical matters.</p><p>(iii) Executive class: They are responsible for implementation of government policies.</p><p>(iv) Clerical class: They carry out clerical duties in the ministry.</p><p>(v) Auxiliary/Manipulative class: They comprise of carpenters, cleaners, etc.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 6,
        "year": 2012,
        "question": "<p>Identify any six features of the igbo traditional societies. </p>",
        "answer": "<p>(I) Decentralized administration.</p><p>(ii) The village was the highest unit of administration.</p><p>(iii) Existence of village assembly (Oha-na-eze/Umunna).</p><p>(iv) The village priest/diviner wielded great deal of religious and judicial powers.</p><p>(v) Significant position of age grades.</p><p>(vi) The family heads played important role in the administration of the village.</p><p>(vii) Title holders (Ozo title) played significant role in the traditional political system.</p><p>(viii) Decisions were reached by consensus.</p><p>(ix) Succession to leadership/coming into prominence was based on personal achievements.</p><p>(x) Political significance of deities in providing bonds of unity.</p><p>(xi) There was the existence of Council of Elders (Ama-ala) presided over by the eldest son in the village.</p><p>(xii) The market square served as the village assembly chambers.</p><p>(xiii) The women (Umuada), composed of the first daughter of each family, constituted a socio-political group.</p><p>(xiv) Banishment from the village/escort into the evil forest was the maximum judicial punishment.</p><p>(xv) New Yam Festival was religiously marked, honoured and celebrated annually. </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 7,
        "year": 2012,
        "question": "<p>(a) Define nationalism.</p><p>(b) state any five external factors that aided the growth of nationalism in West Africa.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>(a) Nationalism can be defined as a strong feeling of national consciousness and love/for one's country to handle its own affairs devoid of foreign control and domination.</p><p>(b)(i)Atlantic Charter: The 1941 Atlantic Charter emphasized the right to self-determination by all the peoples of the world.</p><p>(ii) Influence of African Americans like Dr. William Du Bois and Marcus Garvey. They supported decolonization of Africa.</p><p>(iii) The establishment of the United Nations Organization stimulated nationalist movements due to its stance on colonialism and Human Rights.</p><p>(iv) Independence of India in 1947 inspired West African Nationalists in the struggle to stamp out colonialism.</p><p>(v) British Labour Party supported self-rule for the colonized territories.</p><p>(vi) The Activities of the West African Student's Union (W.A.S.U) in Britain and the U.S.A.</p><p>(vii) The role played by the US and the former USSR in the decolonization agitation.</p><p>(viii) The defeat of Britain by Japan.</p><p>(ix) The activities of the Pan-African Congress.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 8,
        "year": 2012,
        "question": "<p>Identify any four features of the policy of indirect rule in West Africa.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>(i) Recognition and use of some traditional rulers/Emirs.</p><p>(ii) Warrant chiefs were appointed in Igboland.</p><p>(iii) The use of native laws and customs.</p><p>(iv) Resident officers/provincial commissioners were appointed to administer the provinces.</p><p>(v) District commissioners were appointed to administer the districts.</p><p>(vi) Native courts administered traditional laws.</p><p>(vii) Native treasures served as custodians of taxes collected.</p><p>(viii) Existence of taxation.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 9,
        "year": 2012,
        "question": "<p>Identify six features  of the macpherson constitution of 1951</p>",
        "answer": "<p>(i) Council of Ministers was constituted and charged with the responsibility of executing policies.</p><p>(ii) Supremacy of the central legislature over regional legislature.</p><p>(iii) Increase in the membership of the central legislature.</p><p>(iv) It provided for a central legislature and executive council for the country.</p><p>(v) It provided for an Executive made up of 18 members.</p><p>(vi) Each region was also provided with regional Executive Council.</p><p>(vii) It also provided for a regional legislative council for each region.</p><p>(vii) Provided for regional houses of chiefs for the northern and western regions.</p><p>(ix) It introduced a new electoral system.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 10,
        "year": 2012,
        "question": "<p>(a) Describe the formation of the Nigeria National Alliance (NNA) of 1964</p><p>(b) Highlight five achievements of the alliance</p>",
        "answer": "<p>(a)(i) NNA was formed on August 20, 1964 to contest the general elections of that year.</p><p>(ii) The political parties that joined to form the Alliance included: NPC, NNDP, Mid-Western Democratic Front (MDF), the Niger Delta Congress (NDC) and the Dynamic Party.</p><p>(iii) The Alliance was led by the Premier of Northern Region, Sir Ahmadu Bello.</p><p>(iv) NNA was formed to counter UPGA which was formed in June 1964.</p><p>(b)(i) It won more seats than the UPGA in the 1964 elections.</p><p>(ii) The Alliance formed the government at federal level after the 1964 general elections.</p><p>(iii) It also participated in the Western Regional election of 1965 through Akintola-led Nigeria National Democratic Party (NNDP).</p><p>(iv) It formed a national government in 1964.</p><p>(v) It participated in the northern general elections of 1965 through NPC.</p><p>(vi) It formed the government of Western Region in 1965.</p><p>(vii) It formed the government of Northern Region in 1965.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 11,
        "year": 2012,
        "question": "<p>Identify any six factors affecting Nigeria foreign policy. </p>",
        "answer": "<p> (i) <strong>History: </strong>Nigeria has a strong link with Britain and some western European powers due to her colonial experience.</p><p>(ii) <strong>Geography:</strong> The location of Nigeria in West Africa determines her relationship with other countries.</p><p>(iii) <strong>Population:</strong> Nigeria is a diverse country with large population and this affects her foreign policy.</p><p>(iv) <strong>National Interest:</strong> Security of lives, territorial integrity and socio-economic developments as part of Nigeria national interest influence her foreign policy.</p><p>(v) <strong>Natural resources:</strong> Nigeria has one of the largest concentration of natural resources in the world. This greatly influences her foreign policy.</p><p>(vi)<strong> Public opinion:</strong> The general views of the Nigerian people are often considered in her foreign policy objectives.</p><p>(vii) <strong>Military strength:</strong> Nigeria has relative military capabilities in Africa. This has been used to influence her foreign policy.</p><p>(viii) <strong>Personality of the leader: </strong>The personality of the Nigeria president is seen as a major influence of the country's foreign policy.</p><p>(ix) The type of government in power also determines the foreign policy direction.</p><p>(x) Membership of Nigeria in international organizations e.g. AU, ECOWAS, etc</p><p>(xi) Nigeria's foreign policy objectives affects her foreign policy.</p><p>(xii) <strong>Religion:</strong> Both Islam and Christianity affect Nigeria's foreign policy.</p><p>(xiii) International laws, conventions and treaties.</p><p>(xiv) Out break of wars and conflict affect Nigeria's foreign policy.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 12,
        "year": 2012,
        "question": "<p>Identify any six problems facing the Economic Community of West African states (ECOWAS)</p>",
        "answer": "<p>(i) Military intervention in politics - West Africa is still bedeviled by military coups. This is seen as a major problem to the community's quest for good and democratic governance.</p><p>(ii) Language barrier: Member states are polarized into English, French and Portuguese languages. This is seen as a barrier to the unity of the peoples of the sub-region.</p><p>(iii) Fear of domination: Some of the smaller nations have great feat that big nations in the community might dominate them. Hence, there is mutual suspicion among them.</p><p>(iv) Influence of foreign powers and ex-colonial masters. Members states depend on them economically.</p><p>(v) Differences in currency: Different currencies create barriers in the exchange of goods and services in the sub-region.</p><p>(vi) Communication problems: Lack of good road network, railway, etc are barriers to economic integration.</p><p>(vii) Economic migrants: Citizens of the economically disadvantaged states migrate to the economically advantaged ones.</p><p>(viii) Inter-state conflict: Inter-state boundary disputes often slow down unity and cooperation within the community.</p><p>(ix) Interference in the internal affairs of member states e.g. Senegal and The Gambia over the Cassamance region of Senegal.</p><p>(x) Inadequate fund due to non-payment of dues by some member states.</p><p>(xi) Low commitment of some political leaders to the ideals of ECOWAS.</p><p>(xii) Influx of refugees lead to social, economic and political problems in the host countries.</p><p>(xiii) Increase in smuggling and illegal trafficking of people and goods.</p><p>(xiv) Similarity of products reduces the chances of the desired economic integration.</p><p>(xv) Existence of rival sub-regional organizations e.g. Mano River Union, CEAO, etc.</p><p>(xvi) ECOWAS has neither standing army nor any other effective instrument of coercion.</p><p>(xvii) Natural disaster like flooding, drought, famine, etc cause great problems to ECOWAS.</p><p>(xviii) Ethnic and religious conflicts. These also cause a great deal of problems to ECOWAS. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    }
]